係嗰次。
意見書。
嗯。
而家第二次會議。
哈哈哈哈哈！
噉啊！誒。
噉我哋文件咧就係誒。
好，我哋夠人又夠足，噉啊！
孫玉涵先生啦，佢係新嘅，因為上次Mabel走咗啦。啊，係喎。
table畀大家嘅就係誒有一份誒。
出釣嘅官員唔一一介紹啦，因為嗰個好多，啊，我哋爭緊時間，好嘛？
因為啲團體代表喺三樓，要等佢啊行落嚟，稍為等等。
噉啊！誒誒，歡迎各團體同埋政府當局嘅代表咧，就誒出席我哋法案委員會嘅會議。噉就誒。
二零一七年打擊洗錢及恐怖分子資金籌集金融機構修訂條例草案及二零一七年公司修訂條例草案委員會。
係。
好嘅。
OK。
你真係讀佢名。
誒，法案委員會嘅聽證會。
誒，好歡迎大家今日出席我哋。
and it may very well be there's an irony.
好啦，噉係請秘書同我安排，誒每位發言咧係三分鐘。
my company had its fintech revolution five years ago. We don't actually use the banking system because we can't.
啊！請你做個宣讀啦。第一位，誒，第一位發言嘅咧就係誒，Mr. Mr.誒，Jason David of呢一個誒，Territorial Express Limited。
bring laws and I don't think the cost of fighting crime is the issue. I think what is the issue here is whether or not the AML laws in practice are succeeding.
and I think that you'll find that the AML laws are the cause of this not only for the type of business which I'm in, but also for other businesses which you're looking at, that's trustees and possibly Comsec.
I'd suggest to you that there are some problem areas that are occurring, and one of them is that in Hong Kong, this I'm sure is not news to everybody, is the difficulty in obtaining and operating bank accounts.
好啦，我仲要提醒下各位誒代表咧，誒今日你哋嚟我哋立法會發言咧，係唔受到權力及特權條例所保障嘅，包括你哋發言同埋你哋嘅文稿。
我喺呢度提醒下誒各位出席嘅團體代表，如果你哋已經準備咗發言稿嘅，請喺你哋離開會議室之前咧誒，將你哋嘅發言稿交畀我哋秘書處嘅職員啊，畀我哋委員會參考。
How do you bypass the banking system? Well, in most of the world now, the use of API, application programming interfaces, and what is now commonly called blockchain methodology, which is not just to do with cryptocurrencies, is becoming commonplace.
誒阿Mabel走咗之後咧，今日新嚟嘅新鮮嘅孫玉涵先生啊，呢個係誒我哋財經事務及副務局嘅副秘長啊，就歡迎你。好多謝主席，因為我哋見過面好多次啦，傾傾偈，我唔記得你呢度係新嘅。好嘅。
Okay, thank you. Next.
Take for example, all of the.
總會嘅嚴志明教授。
all of the accountants.
誒跟住嘅係香港工業總。
and therefore, I would recommend to the Bills Committee two things.
Will perhaps cease business because they're unable to continue on.
A lot of businesses that could call themselves trustees, and certainly Comsac.
主席，各位議員，我代表香港工業總會就修訂條例草案發表意見。
couple of other remarks. Five years ago, there were approximately 11,000 remittance companies in Hong Kong.
that the AML laws as they are conceived at the moment will abolish a 19th century banking system in pretty short order, and I think we need to be prepared for that.
One is that they look at the general criminalisation of failure to comply with AML by service providers, and the other is to take a hard look at whether or not the paperwork is worth the candle. Thank you very much.
要求跨國企業披露實益擁有權嘅資料，建立一個可供查閲嘅實益擁有權登記冊，以至各國嘅税務機關建立呢個資料嘅交換機制咧，已經成為國際推動税務透明嘅趨勢。
One last comment: the AML laws in practice do impose a cost, and all of that I said at the beginning. I don't think the cost of fighting crime is the issue. It costs whatever it costs to try to succeed, but that battle will never be won.
Chairman and members, thank you for the opportunity. My company is a remittance company and has been dealing with AML issues for a very long time. I also deal with pension payment systems and also in the area of trustees. We all know the purpose of the anti-money laundering.
There are now less than a thousand, and and I spoke to the customs about this phenomenon after the Amel laws were brought in five years ago. They smiled sweetly at me and said that's a police problem. So I think you will find that as a result of this legislation that you're looking at.
多謝。好，多謝你。你。
誒下一個咧係香港特許秘書公會嘅高朗先生。
企企業識別同埋確定實益擁有權嘅資料，可能存在嘅困難。
In 2008， we already set AML CFT standards. That's almost a decade ago.
亦都確保我哋公司能夠咧誒充分瞭解同埋實實施新個規定，以免影響公司嘅運作嘅。
有關嘅修訂咧，需要提供可行嘅安排嚟到處理呢啲嘅情況嘅。第二就係登記冊制度嘅實施。
Then in 2016, following Panama Papers, HAICS further set standards for members engaged in the TCSP sector.
800 members and 3,200 students, and these standards that we set revolve around good governance, which our members as governance professionals champion.
重要控制人嘅登記冊呢個制度咧係新事物，公眾認為咧，當局必須對相關嘅法例條文咧制定清晰嘅指引，亦都要配備充足嘅宣傳。
行嘅，以及要盡量減低規管對企業經營嘅影響，同埋中巡規管嘅成本。其中公眾對以下三點咧感到係關注嘅，第一就係。
工作向香港嘅公司咧，詳細介紹呢個登記冊嘅制度。我哋建議當局應該採取以風險為本嘅規管，以一套客觀可行嘅標準評估公司嘅風險狀況，將規管嘅工作咧集中喺最高風險嘅公司，而避免成為擾民嘅措施。
由於香港需要履行打擊洗錢同埋恐怖分子籌集資金方面嘅國際責任，因此公眾對條例嘅修訂係表示認同嘅，以免影響咗香港喺國際評級上面有負面嘅影響。但係另一方面咧，公眾認為有關修訂咧必須確實確保係實際可。
喺實際操作情況底下咧，香港公司只可能披露直接持有該公司股份嘅海外人士嘅身份。至於嗰啲通過海外公司間接擁有該公司股份嘅人士咧，香港公司要求呢啲海外公司提供佢哋擁誒擁有其重大控制權人士嘅資料咧，可能會有實際嘅困難。所以咧。
第三就係失誤資料嘅懲處，修訂法案建議公司咧唔遵從誒備存重要控制人登記冊呢個規定，公司同埋佢嘅每名責任人咧可以被罰款嘅，最高係兩萬五，另外每日係七百。而若果呢個重要控制人登記冊有誤導性或者，
虛假或者佢有欺騙性嘅陳述咧，就可以罰款三十萬同埋監禁兩年嘅。咁呢個懲處可以話都係幾重嘅。工種認為咧，中小企近年嘅經營咧已經十分困難，偶有疏忽咧，好難在所難免。如果發現登記冊資料有誤咧，法例應該畀個機會佢哋更正。如果公司喺合理期限內，
都未可以更正資料，或者隻證據顯示呢啲失誤資料咧係屬於蓄意所為咧，執法當局先至可以加以懲處嘅。我哋就總結就係話，公眾希望咧政府能夠充分考慮香港公司嘅實際經營情況，喺令到我哋提升誒實質擁有權呢個透明度嘅同時咧。
Should I start? Yeah. Thank you. Okay，講英文冇意思。噉啊，Hello Ada and Eureka and Chairman and everyone。An important function of a professional body is to set standards for promoting good practice by members. For HKICS, we've got five thousand.
多謝。
柳眉女士。
Whether listed in Hong Kong or overseas.
我們相信，這建議應該不會爭議。
This issue needs to be addressed at the opportune time.
Thank you。啊，下一位係林。
The current position is that anyone over 18 who is not a bankrupt could satisfy that test.
This would deal with the issue of livelihood. I know that there's a worry that people's livelihood would be affected, and this could be dealt with.
and we have set out in our submission that even FATF has stated that there is a need to consider professionalism of the TCSB sector.
In this connection, I would refer you to Singapore position, whereby a person who is experienced and or qualified could be licensed as a TCSP.
所以從這背景，你會gather that HKICS strongly and I emphasise strongly supports both bills， which includes TCSP regulation of which HKICS is a forerunner.
The HKICS AML CFT guidelines follows those of financial institutions, over which the Financial Services Treasury Bureau and also the Narcotics Division provided their input before we published it.
A TCSP cannot be expected to find out who persons of significant control are over listed companies, especially as shares could be held through central clearing, and disclosure regimes differ globally.
The more complex issue is who could become a TCSP, aside from lawyers, accountants and estate agents, who would be self-regulatory, or other TCSP would need to be licensed and regulated by the company's registrar, if they could satisfy a fit and proper test.
Now, without derogation of the generality of our strong support for the bills, we like to turn to matters of details. HAICS has made it known to Financial Services and Treasury Bureau that in respect of identification of persons with significant control, this should stop with identification of a listed company.
If reasons are required for HKICS supports, these are that the legislations are necessary to comply with FATF recommendations 22 and 24, which were brought to the forefront by the Panama Papers scandal, and otherwise required to enhance Hong Kong's international reputation in combating financial crimes.
可以話嗰個誒。
嗯，係多謝。好，唔該曬，下一位。
下一位係律師會嘅黃石紅小姐。
可以話一百二十日嘅誒呢個過渡期咧，噉啊希望誒可以誒放寬嘅。
咁其實誒，下年嗰個可能工作量啊，嗰個誒時間表都好緊闌。噉啊，如果你話希望誒，
誒特別行動啦，噉啊要實施誒兩種呢個草案條例，咁但係亦希望咧就誒政府咧都可以話體諒我哋本本誒行業啦嗰個工作量啦啊，噉就誒。
誒多多謝主席噉啊，同埋多謝誒呢個公司註冊處誒，同埋各國嘅誒即係監管嘅機構啦。噉啊，我只就誒係代表誒，即係我只本本人咧，同埋本業啦。咁呢個係誒佢誒呢個可以話係誒信託話呢個誒。
誒公司服務誒提供者嘅噉，其實都誒即係知道，可能香港誒其實以往畀誒外資誒外或者外商嗰個形象係十分之好嘅誒自由同埋嗰個法制係十分之好誒。咁其實都令到咧，我哋本行咧誒或者本
本本業咧，其實嗰個誒係帶來好多機遇，同埋好蓬勃啦。噉我哋希望咧嗰個誒本業咧係誒成個行業係可以誒有呢個持續誒下去啦。噉啊誒一個好嘅發展。咁但係亦誒可以話體諒咧誒誒監管機構咧，隨住呢個誒。
除咗呢個誒，即係實施呢個發牌之外咧，咁亦係我哋誒本業都要誒有新嘅誒，可以話嗰個誒實質一個誒重要控制人嗰個誒登記冊嘅噉。所以你話誒，如果係誒發牌咧？
係咪？
好，得翻。
Okay, thank you.下一位。
Yes, thank you, Mr. Chairman and Members.
下一個係誒，Law Society of Hong Kong representatives from Law Society of Hong Kong。
下一個係ErnestandYoungAdvisoryServicesLimited嘅代表。Yes，thank you。
That are from a criminal source, as opposed to fulfilling exercises that ultimately just look to tick a box in terms of obtaining a document.
The Law Society's position is that solicitors and foreign lawyers in Hong Kong are already subject to a well-established, effective and enforceable AML regime.
金融機構修訂法案，和至於律師業有關的，亦都係擬議的後續修訂條文，對《律師業條例》。
The Law Society is concerned at the approach taken by the government towards the proposed amendments to the Anti-Money Laundering and Counter-Terrorist Financing
Also, in terms of the move to the twenty-five percent beneficial ownership requirement, that puts it in line with the common reporting standard as well as the FATF recommendations, and so we think these are very good steps in the right direction. Thank you very much.
咁呢個係令到咧公眾係有效可以監察到究竟即係依啲資料嘅即係誒透明度。噉我哋認為依個咧其實係最有用嘅方法咧去誒處理依個問題。謝謝各位。
therefore it's the society's respectful submission that there is no need for solicitors and foreign lawyers to be included in the AMLO amendment bill and there is no need to amend the legal practitioners ordinance either.
嗯，主席你好，啊各位委員好。啊，律師會一直咧就相信貧窮源於不公平。咁税務公義咧，其實係一個非常重要嘅環節。噉我哋一直都倡議咧，跨國企業咧喺報税上邊咧應該增加嗰個資料嘅透明度，咁令到咧其實公眾可以即係監察到。
噉就住政府嘅諮詢嘅總結咧，我哋有三點意見。第一點咧就係誒，我哋留意到咧，其實政府嘅諮詢嘅總結咧並冇包括咧要求信託同埋有限責任合夥咧披露依啲相關資料。咁喺巴拿巴文件咧，其實已經披露咗依兩類嘅法律實體咧，往往。
就係用嚟避税個途徑，所以我哋咧就即係認為應該係有必要同時規管咧信託同埋有限責任合夥。事實上，新加坡咧其實喺今年三月咧都已經通過咗多項嘅法律修訂咧，要求無論係公司誒依兩類即係信託同埋有限責任合夥咧，都要披露呢啲beneficial。
ownership嘅，第二咧就係啊，雖然政府其實話根據咗咧財務行動特別組織嘅建議咧，就要求beneficial owners咧，其實個門檻咧就擺喺公司股份或者投票權嘅二十五嘅percent，我哋咧就必須要提各位咧，其實呢個二十五嘅percent咧，只係一個舉例，並唔係一個咧。
規定嘅指引喺歐盟咧，其實今年年尾都討論緊咧。誒第五項反洗錢嘅指令上邊咧，最大改動就係將二十五個percent降到十個percent。我哋要求咧，其實誒應該將嗰個門檻降到甚至低於五個percent，同咧而家。
證券及期貨條例咧界定大股東嘅門檻咧係睇齊嘅。最後啦，就係我哋關於咧就係誒嗰個公眾查閲咧嗰個問題，因為而家咧其實使用嘅權咧個資料咧政府就話都係即係誒誒唔會擺喺公司註冊處，我哋認為應該要擺公司。
Thank you.
thank you，next。
白事樓。
on customer due diligence and record keeping.
誒，下一個係香港信託人公司嘅代表邵偉求先生。
律師會 respectfully disagrees with the government's interpretation of the FATF recommendations.
Furthermore, the prescriptive nature of the proposed requirements in AMLO amendment bill goes.
The other deficiency relates to beneficial ownership information of legal entities and trusts. We don't comment on the latter here.
The Law Society says that the implementation of Pact as Direction P, it has established over its members or by, I beg your pardon.
Against the risk-based approach prominently mandated by FATF, and will provide no significant or tangible benefits in the fight against money laundering.
Practice Direction P satisfies FATAS recommendations. It has the effect of law and is enforceable by sanctions, which are effective, proportionate and dissuasive.
We would welcome the opportunity to address this committee in greater detail to explain why this amendment is unnecessary as a matter of textual interpretation of FATF recommendations.
With the implementation of Practice Direction P, it has established over its members a legal AML mechanism which is fully compliant with FATF's recommendation.
The Hong Kong government says that the law society's current AML regulation in the form of Practice Direction P, issued on 3 December 2007, does not comply with FATF recommendations.
The rigid approach advocated by the Hong Kong government will create an unnecessary compliance burden on the legal profession in Hong Kong, which contrasts unfavorably with the current approach taken by Practice Direction P.
註冊處令到公眾可以查閲喺德國同國耳蘭咧，依啲國家咧都係根據咧反黑展嘅指令咧，係嗯將依個即係誒具有正當權益嘅公眾人士查閲咧依個病例file咧，擺喺中央政策即係中央嘅查查冊裏邊嘅。
Yes, thank you very much for having me here. So we just like to express our support for the bill. We think that the 25% beneficial ownership requirement, along with the address proof being removed in terms of a bill copy, is a very strong.
And beneficial thing for facilitating account opening from a as well as periodic review from a onboarding perspective and customer maintenance perspective within the banking industry. Also, it will allow for the banks to take more of a risk-based approach to money laundering, which will hopefully lead to more funds being interdicted.
The Hong Kong government has identified two deficiencies in Hong Kong's regime when compared with the Financial Action Task Force (FATF) recommendations. One of these deficiencies relates to the absence of customer due diligence and record keeping requirements for designated non-financial businesses and professions.
Finish.
Thank you. Time's up.
When CTSPs are to be regulated by law.
Before I move on, a couple of specific items in the bills, the HKTA would like to emphasise that.
This arrangements can facilitate a smooth transition and are appropriate.
We are pleased that the FSB, the government, has made considerable effort to consult the industry, for examples by way of briefing sessions and meetings, and seek industry views in respect of the matters relating to the bills.
Various concerns raised by the industry via our submissions and face-to-face discussions have been dealt with and reflected in the bill. We will continue to support the government by giving comments on the draft guidelines issued by the company registry.
Under the existing MLO, trust companies have been helping financial institutions on the required due diligence work, and that HKTA did issue best practice guides setting out AML and CDD principles to educate and raise industry standards of its members.
For Hong Kong to demonstrate that our trusts and company structures are used for proper purposes. To the industry, the proposed legislation is as important as the reform of the trust law enacted in the Legislative Council in 2013, for purposes of strengthening the competitiveness of Hong Kong's trust services industry.
Hi, hi, Mr. Chairman. Good afternoon. I'm pleased to have opportunity to give views on the bills on behalf of the Hong Kong Trustees Association (HKTA). The association encompasses various sectors of the trust industry, corporate trusts, pension schemes, private trust.
和慈善信託，我們協會是支持該立法的指引，第一，來增強受益所有人擁有香港公司的透明度；第二，來規範法定的客户盡職調查（CDD）給信託公司。這不是一件很漂亮的東西，而是需要。
as for specific items, first, the extended grace period from ninety days to one hundred and twenty days for existing trust companies to apply for the licence, and the deem licensing arrangement whereby existing trust companies will get the licence as so long as they send in the application within the one hundred and twenty.
誒。
Thank you. Okay, next.
for trusts and corporate services providers.
代表從Clifford Chance。
that a new licensing regime be instituted.
跟住係卓佳專業商務有限公司嘅代表。
yes, thank you. I'm Natalia Sand, representing Tricol Services Limited.
和customer due diligence， and record keeping requirements under the AML ordinance as it exists.
這些受託人是受資格或註冊於SFC，已受SFC的適格及適當性測試。
我們suggest that such TCSPs be granted an exemption from the proposed new licensing requirement.
被要求要取得額外的許可證，從公司登記處，所以他們可以提供那些信託和公司服務。
similarly, although there is no dedicated regulatory body with statutory power to manage AML compliance of firms or corporates providing trust or company formation services in Hong Kong, some TSCPs are already subject to the oversight of the financial regulator.
We agree that there is credit in introducing a licensing regime for these TCSPs. However, whilst not mandatory, some Hong Kong incorporated companies are already registered as trust companies under the Trusty Ordinance.
第二，The provision to allow financial institution to carry out CDD by means of a trust and corporate services providers (CTSPs) as specified intermediaries is indeed in line with those applicable law under the existing AMLO and and the FADIF, the Financial Action Task.
第三，as regards to CDD requirements for CTSPs customers who are not physically present, that is non-face-to-face account opening, it will be okay having regard to the money laundering risk, but subject to additional measures for identification verification. Fourth, in many jurisdictions, the beneficial ownership registration
是 not open to the public. I think this is something that we will also support, and as well as a threshold from 10 to 25% on determine the beneficial ownership. So we would really believe that the government's consultation document mentioning the principle of balanced approach, we the significance of this to complement the need to have effective.
委員會的強制執行系統，而addressing concerns to minimise regulatory burden and compliance costs on business. To conclude, it is a must for the passage of the bills to reinforce Hong Kong as a well-regarded international financial centre, and we is committed to work with the government for the smooth implementation of this important amendment.
Thank you. I'm here today to speak on behalf of my firm Clifford Chance, and we we too support this initiative because it's going to obviously help improve Hong Kong's credibility and standing as an international financial centre. I just have a couple of very high level comments that I'd like to provide in connection with the proposal.
and in our view, and consistent with financial action taskforce which supports a risk-based approach to TCSPs, we think that the TCSPs registered under the trust ordinance and those already subject to licensing registration requirements of the financial regulator should not.
呃，富摩雅公司，we are a trust and corporate service provider. So basically, our firm we do support the two initiatives, that is the licensing of the TCSP and also the introduction of the the register of the significant controller. the
今天，謝謝。
跟跟住嘅係地產代理監管局嘅代表啊，梁德麗女士。
the register in response to the requirement of the OECD. All these two initiatives, we do we do see that that will help Hong Kong to
to to enhance our position as an international financial centre. One observation I like to mention is that on the registration on the licensing of the TCSP, at this moment it is just anybody who is above the age of eighteen and not bankrupt. But that I think.
作為第一步，我們支持這，但going forward， to be honest， to run a TCSP these days， more efforts， more resources will need to be built in， because you you need you need a lot of training， staff training， you need to to know the law， follow very closely about the new legislative.
Requirements and it is not just anybody who is above the age of eighteen that is not a bankrupt that is interested in running the business would run the business well. So I think going forward, if there are suitable opportunities, we really like the government to consider situation in other part of the world.
That is more enhanced requirement, like at least the person running the business, there will be professionals there because the professionals are subject to disciplinary power, and then they will be more concerned with all the regulatory requirement that is needed to run properly a TCSP. That's what I want to mention.
多謝主席。誒，地產代理監管局，以下我簡稱為監管局，完全明白政府為咗履行香港作為財務行動特別組織成員嘅國際責任，需要加強打擊洗錢同埋恐怖分子資金籌集嘅監管制度。雖然監管局支持政府有關方面工作，但係同時關注條例裡面有關客户盡職審查同埋備存記錄嘅規定點樣。
能夠切實有效噉樣喺地產代理業界落實，而監管局作為規管者，能夠喺執行嘅時候唔會有太大困難，亦都係重要嘅。首先係關於執行簡化盡職審查嘅意見，地產代理係低風險嘅行業，因為代理喺處理客户金錢方面角色，多數只係限於喺簽訂立約嘅時候，將客户嘅臨時訂金支票，通常係留低嘅三至五個percent交畀賣方或者。
即賣方嘅律師以現金繳付臨時訂金係極為少有嘅，因此金管局認為條例嘅賦權條文即第七條要夠闊，令金管局可以因按行業因應面對相對較低嘅風險狀況，制定適當同埋實際嘅指引，並容許地產代理喺低風險嘅情況之下，例如非現金交易、政府資助房屋買賣等等，執行簡化。
客户盡職審查，但係綜合條例嘅附權條文附表二第二部第三條同第四條嘅內容，非金融業人士似乎就只係能夠喺第四條嗰啲定明嘅情況之下，例如客户係政府、金融機構、上市公司或者係公共機構，先至可能可以執行簡化客户盡職審查，亦即係話適用嘅情況係極為少。所以今個建議收。
嗯。
誒，主席，各位，大家好。
查閲有關嘅登記，影響公司嘅運作。
擁有有關公司百分之三十嘅股份同埋投票權。
我代表香港中華輸入口商會表達對兩條草案嘅意見。
香港中華出入口商會嘅代表彭楚夫先生。
啊，同埋可以有權委任罷免個半數公司董事嘅人士為重要控制人。
噉啊，有關誒公司，有關公司百分之二十五嘅股份或者投票權。
咁而家現時一般大家所啊明瞭嘅上市規則中有關控股股東嘅定義咧，就係控。
雖然係噉樣樣，誒中出對工資條例中有關重要控制人嘅定義咧，係有個別嘅意見嘅。
誒本會中出原則上咧認同同埋支持兩條草案嘅誒條例草案。首先，香港作為一個國際金融大都會，本身就有責任履行。
啊！另外咧，亦都《公司條例草案》裏面規定有關重要控制人登記冊，噉啊，呢個呢個冊只係需要放喺公司裏面，而且只係有執法人員喺執。
啊！而且控股股東嘅地位咧，同公司條例中有關嘅重要控制人嘅定位咧，係啊非常相似，所以都希望當局咧可以考慮會唔會啊會啊避免咗一個混淆咧，將呢個重要控制人。
冇修定法例，冇業界嘅支持同埋接納嘅情況之下，監管局亦都唔能夠輕易噉樣調高排費，所以監管局要動用本身嘅資金去承擔執行新法例所涉及嘅額外資源，而咁亦都可能對監管局構成財政方面嘅壓力同埋困難。以上係監管局誒嘅睇法同埋意見。多謝。好，唔該曬，下一位。
誒加強打擊洗黑錢嘅國際責任，而且喺呢兩條草案裏邊咧，亦都幫助到政府咧可以有效有效監察不明對眼資金嘅流動，亦都可以防止不法分子利用空殼公司進行洗黑錢同埋籌集恐怖主義活動資金嘅目的。
定相關條文，容讓監管機構可以喺考慮行業嘅業務性質同埋風險狀況之後，除咗第四條定明嘅情況之外，就相關界別人士可以採取簡化客户進職審查嘅情況，發出指引。另外，關於誒發出行業指引方面，喺唔損害剛剛所表達嘅意見嘅前提之下，監管局感謝政府加入賦權條文。今
官局會依賴賦權條文，因應唔同類型物業交易嘅性質同埋風險狀況，並喺考慮地產代理以下獨特嘅情況之後，發出務實嘅指引，包括程序方面，例如進行公司查冊或者係核實實益擁有人身份嘅方式同埋深度，以便發出嘅指引係代理能夠合理地遵守得到嘅。一代理嘅技能水平，佢哋入行嘅學歷要求。
投資係中午或者同等嘅教育程度，而執行客户盡職審查嘅費用喺某啲情況之下都可以好高嘅，例如海外公司查冊或者多層嘅公司查冊，代理嘅營運成本無疑會加重，尤其是係細行。另外，地產代理係收取佣金嘅，其中已經包括佢哋所有嘅開支，佢哋難以好似律師噉樣將有關費用咧轉嫁畀客户，以代佔付嘅形。
費用嘅形式收取，同埋三當林若喺極為緊迫嘅情況之下，時間商議或者簽署嘅時候，代理實際上都有可能係冇足夠嘅時間喺簽約嘅時候完成慣常嘅後續式審查。最後想提一提監管局資源方面嘅影響。截至二零一七年九月，地產代理持牌人數為三萬八千二百九十四。更
監管局並非由政府資助，收入來源係牌照費用。喺法律實施之後，要執行相關嘅規管工作，例如額外嘅合規巡查、投訴調查、記錄言訊等等，都要涉及額外嘅人手同埋開支。但係同時，監管局誒要注意咧喺履行佢嘅核心職能嘅效率方面，唔能夠因為額外嘅規管工作而受到影響喺。
執行特定嘅目的嗰陣時先可以查閲，咁中出對呢一樣誒呢一個安排咧係誒贊同嘅。噉啊一方面咧係可以加強嗰個監察同埋保障公司嘅運作，啊另外一方面咧對嗰個私隱方面都能夠取得平衡，避免其他別有用心嘅人士可以隨時。
啊，有關。
到點就接。啊，到點，next。
作為那些被規管本身。
跟住係誒Step Hong Kong Limited嘅代表。
擁有相關公司嗰個股份咧，提升到百分之三十。
有權委任同埋罷免過半數公司董事嘅人設嘅定義。
噉啊！與此同時咧，誒亦都希望當局咧能夠誒説明清楚同埋界定咧。
We support the need, on the other hand, for confidentiality and privacy, for the vast majority of the users of these services.
We are very much in support of the two bills. We recognise the need for transparency and compliance in what we're.
What we're doing, we want to have a clear and consistent global framework to root out tax evasion and other crimes.
所以一般嚟誒總括嚟講，我哋中出中華出入口商會咧係支持呢兩項誒條例草案，咁但係亦都希望當局咧可以考慮頭先我哋本會嘅意見。
噉啊，有關人士是否需要任何嘅文書嘅協議？如果有關人士係可以有權委任或者拜免過半數公司嘅董事，又冇任何嘅文書或者協議，咁點樣去證明咧？
On the same in the same line, we represent those people whose information will be collected, as well as those doing the collection. So we are somewhat unique in this position in terms of speaking on behalf of both sides of the users and the providers of the services that are being regulated.
Thank you very much, Chairman. Thank you very much to the committee members and most of all the government departments in helping push together this very comprehensive bill, the bills and taking this to the effort in a very short period of time in order to maintain Hong Kong at the forefront of the financial services industry. Step stands for
Society for Tax and Estate Practitioners. We are a global organisation of over twenty thousand individual members, consisting of lawyers, accountants, bankers, trustees, and trustees from big and small. So we comprise both the users of the services that's being regulated.
噉。
嗯。
The.
幾年嘅公司法。
Clients and our members.
But this is an important first step for us to get there.
That concludes my our submission on behalf of STEP. Thank you.
We also need to safeguard information that's being collected, and.
No, thank you. Next, Mr. Anthony Rodgers.
We want to have, as expressed by some of the other people present today, substantive regulation of the trustees.
我們每日顧問有關個人安全、從騷擾、從訴訟、煩瑣的聲索。
We support the idea of not centralising the information in one place, so that it's less easy to tap into, hack into, and have access on a more global basis.
The law has never gone beyond the shareholders of a company. Now there is some recognition of that in section 6653ZF.
On specific changes to the bills and the guidelines, we suggest aligning some of the timetable to be consistent with existing companies ordinance guidelines, and we will make a formal submission to the drafters in order to outline what we propose there.
A lot of our clients are involved in estate planning, so we want to make sure they are shielded from estate fights amongst the families, divorces, planning for the future. That is our task. The provision of this information to the public would be very detrimental to the personal security of our clients.
Mr. Chairman, members of the committee, thank you very much. I am here in my personal capacity. Although in earlier years I've been here as the chairman of the Standing Committee on Law Reform on Company Law Reform, and also as the company's judge in the.
Those days, one thing I would like—I don't want to repeat my written submission to you—but one thing I would like to emphasise is that the register of significant controllers is a significant departure from 160.
O.K.
嗯。
嗯，第呢？
一樣嘢就係話，如果係。
咁亦或係一個總嘅公司就可以監概括曬所有嘅辦事處咧？
跟住係誒偉通註冊有限公司嘅朱耀光先生。
持牌人多於一個營業地址咧，係咪每一個誒地址都要獨立去申請個牌照咧？
To that register being open to public inspection.
It is. It should be confidential. And I'm sorry, I disagree with people who have said otherwise this afternoon.
But it may not go far enough, and we may be opening the floodgates of considerable litigation, which we haven't realised. So I'd like to bear that in mind. Secondly, I would be most averse.
Hold by husbands and wives, and they just own their their their flat or some or their house or whatever it happens to be, or it's a trading company and it's perfectly obvious who the significant controllers are. There is no need for every company to have a register of significant controllers.
As far as I'm concerned, a lot of that, and I've told you why, is going to be worthless bits of paper because most of that information is public record anyway, because it's the shareholders. It's only some companies, out of the million or.
also companies or million or more companies which include all the private companies there are more than a million of them in Hong Kong, all the guarantee companies and all the unlimited companies, out of those very few are going to have to have a register, if this
If my proposal is that only those companies which need a register of significant controllers is adopted, that would save an awful lot of trouble. You're going to, because you've got to realise that a lot of companies are.
The only other thing I would add is not on this ordinance, but on the service provider ordinance. As far as I can see, it's simply, as Natalia was suggesting, window dressing. It's going to achieve very little because anybody can get registered.
係誒主席，我哋誒好同意公司法處呢個監管嘅條例嘅誒進行嘅。咁但係咧喺個條例裏邊咧冇講到咧，我哋嘅持牌人咧要喺個營業地點度咧係將嗰個得誒牌照係展示畀人哋睇到，知道佢有冇真係攞到牌照，同埋另外。
唔該，好。
做作為公司秘書咧。
營運嘅公司咧，完全係不受監管嘅。
有限公司，但係如果係一啲境外。
咁另外誒喺誒。
咁另外仲有一樣就係話喺發牌之後會唔會再加強個人營運者嘅監管，等於地產代理咁有個人牌咧？
風險名單度咧，令到大家嘅從業員更加清晰知道有邊啲國家係高危，或者係有誒對任何一方面都係有損害咧。
呢啲公司點樣去誒處理咧？因為啲細都有細規模嘅誒秘書公司，或者係service provider，未必有能力係請唔同嘅人去做唔同嘅角色。
咁喺第二樣咧，就係話喺誒今次嘅監管裏邊咧，淨係監管喺香港成立嘅公司，或者係一啲誒團體，或者係誒。
FAST裏邊咧，每一季咧，並保安局或者禁毒處咧，就會發出一個個高危國家嘅指引。咁公司註冊處會唔會將呢個指引都列埋落去TCSP嘅誒？
FedF recommendation to establish customer due diligence and record keeping requirement for DNFBPs. This is to avoid potential misuse of these professions in concealing the identities of the beneficial owners of the transaction done through them.
咁對於呢啲嘅情形下咧，誒喺誒條例發生之後，會唔會係考慮去修改個條例，令到喺海外營運嘅地嘅公司或者係團體都受到監管咧？甚至係喺誒未來嘅日子，所有香港嘅公司一定要委任一個持牌。
咁對於一啲我哋比較細嘅誒TCSP嘅公司嚟講咧，咁個合規主任同埋嗰個洗錢報告主任，或者係誒持牌人，會唔會係同一個人咧？如果係可以同一個人嘅情形，或sorry應該話唔可以係同一個情形，同一個人嘅情形下，咁？
跟住係香港銀行公會嘅代表何家全先生。嗯，Chairman啊，Members of Committee，on behalf of the Hong Kong Association of Banks (H. Cap)，啊，I thank for the Bill's Committee for the opportunity to provide H. Cap's view in relation to our due to the proposed amendment to the AML.
Ordinance. First and foremost, HKCAB strongly supports to the bill and the ongoing initiative to make the Hong Kong's ML regime more balanced and responsive to the evolving nature of the money laundering risk. HKCAB has been working closely with our regulator and the government to advocate for changes on behalf.
Half of the banking industry, we acknowledge that the bill primarily focuses on expanding the existing AML requirement to designated non-financial business and professions (DNFBPs). In our view, this aligns Hong Kong's AML requirement with long-standing financial action tasks for.
as possible.
Okay, thank you. Next.
historically been subject to such requirement.
跟住係金瑞豐企業諮詢有限公司嘅楊婉琪小姐。
to detect and prevent money laundering and terrorist financing, which is in the best interest of Hong Kong as an IFC. That concludes my view. Thank you, Chairman.
We suggest to abolish Section 653B 1J in order to avoid confusion as well as abusive of power by an officer of any department or agency of the government.
It is also consistent with FEDS and the international community's increased focus on improving the implementation of international standards, particularly with respect to the business which have not.
Other than the above major change, we are also pleased to see, amongst other things, three other important amendment to the AML ordinance. First, the bill will allow a new category of eligible intermediaries to help with AML due diligence process.
Due diligence process. Not only does this proposed amendment better align the ordinance with Recommendation 17 of the FATF recommendations, but it also means that Hong Kong can make onboarding process faster, easier and more convenient for international customer.
Specifically, certain related foreign financial institutions may become eligible intermediary, as proposed in Section 18 of Schedule 2 of their AML ordinance. This new category will allow many of our HCAP members that operate in international banking groups to utilise more group members in their network to help with the.
HKB strongly supports the proposed amendment and is consistent with the implementation of financial inclusion. Secondly, with respect to the removal of requirement for verified address to be included in the payment message of wire transfer as proposed in section 12 of Schedule 2 of the bill, based on the existing reg.
That is to obtain address proof each time the bank customer wish to transfer money using the most conservative interpretation. This would have create a negative user experience, particularly in the in the context of long standing customer relation. We are therefore very supportive of the proposed change. Thirdly, the amendment to the definition.
beneficial owner moving from 10% to over 25%, also help to align with the international standard. Overall, I would like to reiterate that the HKC support believe that the enhanced regime foster a stronger and compliant regulatory environment. This ultimately enhance Hong Kong's system systemic ability.
Good afternoon, everyone. Thank you for inviting me to participate in this meeting. EastWest is a corporate services provider, and we fully support and welcome the proposal for of introducing the licensing regime for trust and corporate services providers, and look forward to the introduction of this licensing regime as soon.
OK。
嗯，thank you.
Section 653B1J。
細節條款 of the bill have been finalised.
Thank you, Chair, for the opportunity to address the committee.
我會 mention 幾個點從我們提交的法案。
將的Beneficial Ownership of the legal entity to a natural person.
下一位，跟住係香港會計師公會嘅丁偉全先生。
實 practising certificate is required in order to conduct statutory audit services in Hong Kong. The institute has more than 42,000 members.
The Hong Kong Institute of CPAs is the only body authorised by law to register, regulate and grant practising certificates to CPAs in Hong Kong.
The Institute is in support of the introduction of legislation to prescribe AML requirements for DNFBPs, in order to minimise the risk of abuse of Hong Kong's financial system by money launderers or terrorists.
We have the following two specific questions in relation to the company's amendment bill 2017, section 653B1J. It is helpful that definitions of the law enforcement officer has been spelled out under section 653B1A to I. However,
It is too broad to empower every officer agency or statutory body of the government to inspect the register of significant controllers. For example, will RCHK fall under the above definition and be able to inspect the to inspect the register of significant controllers?
If RTHK has been allowed to inspect the register of significant controllers, other media may think that they would be disadvantaged and question the reason why RTHK has been granted with such exclusive power. In any event, what is the need of granting RTHK the power to inspect the register of?
significant controllers. This is just an example. Professional firms have the duty to explain and persuade the clients to comply and prepare a significant controllers register. When the clients ask us who have the right to inspect the significant controllers register, we can easily provide the name of.
The organisations by referring to section six hundred and fifty three B one A to I, it will be difficult to identify who the other organisations are in relation to section six hundred and fifty three B one J, and hence this will create confusion and misunderstanding. So we strongly suggest to delete.
第二點， significant controllers register。 我們理解到， 一個 significant controller 可能是自然人或法律實體。 請釐清， 如果法律實體被允許成為 significant controller 在登記冊， 是否有必要追蹤。
In anticipation of the bill, the institute has already drawn up draft AML guidelines and consulted our members on them. The guidelines will be part of our enforceable code of ethics, and non-compliance with them may result in the institute taking disciplinary actions against institute members and/or CPA firms. The guidelines will be finalised one.
嚇！啊，第一個咧就係。
We are also in support of the company's amendment bill.
跟住嘅係阿Coat Limited嘅陳建平先生。
which will enhance transparency of company ownership. I will just mention two of the points.
The AML requirements relating to accounting profession in the bill we apply only to our members.
details of the share regulatory arrangements between the institute and administration will need to be developed.
The existing ordinance was drawn up with FIs in mind and catered specifically for the circumstances of FIs.
We will have a clear understanding whether this approach is sufficient to meet the FEDAF requirements after the mutual evaluation of Hong Kong has been conducted in 2018.
We also suggest the government consider extending access to this register to TnFPs regulated for AML to facilitate them in discharging the CDD obligations. Thank you. Okay, thank you.
啊，主席咁多位嚇，誒本人作為一個誒服務提供者咧，有少少誒對呢個支誒草案支持嘅，咁但係有少少關於呢個發牌同埋嗰個誒盡職審查方面有幾個意見同提問嘅啫。
Under the proposed new section 583 of the AML ordinance, institute members and CPA practices will be regulated by the institute when they prepare for or carry out transaction for clients in relation to certain specified services.
We understand from our discussion with the government that it is sufficient for the institute to respond to complaints against CPAs and CPA practices, and that there is currently no obligation to proactively monitor compliance by members with the proposed AML requirements.
Instead of or in addition to each individual company keeping its own register, we believe that in the long run, Hong Kong should have a central database of registers of persons with significant control to ease information access and help transparency and accuracy.
Therefore, other people, including overseas qualified accountants working in Hong Kong, will not be regulated for AML when they provide the same services, i.e., end of the services referred to in section 5A3A to F. This could result in regulatory and expectation gap.
我們會 prefer to see tailor-made AML legislation for DNFPPs，但 consider that the proposed approach of extending the ordinance to cover DNFPPs should be workable， so long as sufficient clarity and perhaps adjustment may be done to concept， terminology and scope。
We also understand the regulation of licensed trust or company service providers operated by CPAs will be shared between the registrar of companies and the institute. The registrar may take action against the corporate entity itself and refer cases of non-compliance relating to individual CPAs to the institute for handling.
嗯。
Next.
啊，咁第三點咧，關於個盡職審查嗰度啦。
Asian and trusted or company service providers.
法團或者個人咧，需唔需要另外申請一個牌照咧？
啊，第二個情況咧就係咧，如果一間嗯，
係咁多唔該。O K，咁咧等政府先再慢慢答你。
跟住嘅係誒Thompson Roasters嘅Mr. Thomas So。
如果第日有個持誒持牌人安排另外一個誒香港嘅法團或者個人出入另外公司嘅秘書。
噉我哋可唔可以喺呢個情況下就暫時唔同佢哋誒攞呢個進職審查嗰啲資料，或者係甚至乎之後都可以唔攞住咧？
喺而家個過渡期裏邊咧，申請個牌照如果被拒絕嘅話咧，就係即時停止營業嘅。噉我想問下，可唔可以將呢個放寬為呢個誒？
因為我哋嘅客户咧，好多時都係啲誒會計師啊，或者法律嘅專業人士嚟嘅。咁可唔可以？因為通常會經過佢哋誒聯絡啲真正嘅客户。
嘅個職位嘅，我想問一問誒，以呢個呢個擔當呢個職位嗰個法團或者誒個人咧，係冇收取任何費用嘅。咁呢個？
喺誒誒，當佢畀誒拒絕誒申請嗰陣時候咧，佢可以喺繼續去繼續申請啦，仍然繼續營業，直至到呢個過渡期完結，或者係申請到牌照為止。
咁喺我哋嘅可唔可以喺雙方，即係我哋同個律師入會計師嗰方面嗰啲客户方面誒協調之下咧，簡化呢個誒盡職審查程序咧？例如佢哋誒保證咗喺誒當期時，佢已經係同個客户做咗盡職審查啦，或者係會之後會誒跟進翻嘅。
Thank you, Chairman and Committee Members, for the invitation and the opportunity to provide our views. Thomson Reuters support the FSTB's aim to extend the anti-money laundering and counter-terrorist financing regime to a number of new businesses and professions, including solicitors, accountants, real.
啊！
今日好多謝有二十個單位同埋廿四位人士，例如我哋聽證會。
咁而家咧，下面咧，我係邀請政府當局就團體嘅代表提出嘅意見咧，作出初步嘅回應。
more than ever there is a need for effective technical process that identify potential financial crime and money laundering risk to support Hong Kong effort that's making our society safer.
Effective have demonstrated cracking down on the laundering of proceeds of crime is an effective way to identify and mitigate mitigate offences.
啊，李主席。誒，多謝主席。誒，亦都非常之多謝咁多位人士嚟到。誒，今日嚟到咧，就講一講大家對於呢兩條修訂條例草案誒嘅意見嘅。誒。
湯森路透斯扮演一個關鍵角色，在香港和全球協助許多私營企業和私營機構識別潛在風險，於其供應鏈客户和業務。
The need of a robust anti-money laundering framework in Hong Kong is heightened by the recent spates of terrorist attack in Europe and beyond, and the concerns surrounding so-called foreign fighters in some Asia countries.
所以， in conclusion， we're submitting our respond. We draw upon Thomson Reuters global experience and expertise in AML CTF field， as well as our team's regulatory analysis from the world's major financial centre. Thank you. 好，唔該曬。
湯森路透相信，一個有效的AML CTF框架是絕對不可或缺，以保護香港經濟，從危害與金融犯罪、組織犯罪及恐怖主義資金，既國內及國際。
佢譬如新加坡，經做經過咗商户誒評估之後咧，誒好明顯個結果就係，如果你唔將指定嘅非金融業人士納入明文法規嘅話咧，你得到嘅結果係非常之不利嘅，係係冇辦法過到關。咁所以呢度咧，我哋係提出一個睇法，呢個就係針對誒納入與否啦。
An effective AML CTF regime requires a coordinated approach between financial and non-financial sectors and public and private sectors. Regulators, government departments, banks and vendors like Thomson Reuters are all part of an ecosystem that prevents and detects financial crime.
相信大家都明白啦。其實呢兩條例要做嘅最大原因咧，就係我哋要面對啊嚟緊啊喺呢個財務行動特別組織下面咧，啊，我哋要做一個啊相互嘅評估嚇。而我哋都好清楚咧啊，雖然我哋而家針對打擊洗錢同埋啊防止恐怖份。
嘅處理。
有啲好具體嘅問題嘅。
當然有部分人士都提出一啲比較原則性嘅問題嘅。
大部分嘅支持嘅嚇，當然喺細節上面咧，大家有唔同嘅意見。
唔知你有冇誒記錄低，可以作出一個初步回應咧？
誒財務行動特別組所講嘅百分之二十五或之或者以上咧，我就畫咗條線。噉我哋覺得呢條線咧係係合理嘅，亦都畫咗呢條線之後咧，對於我哋去去應對嚟緊嘅相互評估咧，誒誒應該係比較理想嘅做法嚟嘅。
主席，誒，我哋記錄低咗嘅，但係我哋覺得係咪可以喺我哋嚟緊嘅會議書面上再提供一啲資料咧？冇問題，我問問嘢。啊，下面咧就請我哋委員咧誒向團體代表或者政府當局提問啦。噉啊，第一位咧就係阿郭榮亨議員。
自集資方面咧，已經有一個好好好好嘅框架，但係咧，亦都有啲不足之處嘅。其中兩點咧，就係今次兩條例要針對處理嘅問題，就分別咧，就係要將指定嘅非金融業人士納入打擊洗錢嘅嘅框架下邊，而呢個納入嘅方法咧，誒。
根據財務行動特別組嘅要求咧，誒必須係一個明文納入法規嘅，嚇呢一點咧，我哋誒知識又有啲團體咧有唔同嘅睇法，啊，但係我哋提出呢個睇法嘅時候咧，誒係經過詳細嘅考慮，啊，亦都參考咗誒喺最近其他嘅地。
我哋其實做呢條兩條例嘅時候咧，經歷咗喺今年年初一月到三月咧，已經做咗一個諮詢。誒，我哋喺制定而家嘅條文嘅時候咧，係盡量吸納咗喺諮詢過程入邊唔同嘅團體所提出嘅意見。啊，佢哋嘅意見非常之有用。啊，我哋喺盡可能情況下面咧。
都盡量將佢吸納咗，係反映咗喺呢個條文下面嘅。誒，今日參與嘅團體所提嘅意見咧，誒，我哋嘅感覺咧係，正如上次諮詢結果一樣嘅，基本上大多數人人士咧都支持政府提出嘅方向，誒，所秉持嘅原則咧，都係得到大家。
誒總而言咧，我我哋我我哋聽咗咁多意見之後咧，誒會覺得有有好多問題咧。其實大家希望喺做指引嘅時候咧，可以講到出嚟，誒可以處理。噉我哋相信咧，誒針對唔同嘅團體一啲細節嘅擔心咧，通過做指引嘅時候咧，我哋希望可以得到一個比較比較妥。
譬如話誒喺將來喺誒公司法下面，如果你係要有一個誒重要控制人嘅登記冊，究竟係要要公開中央啦，定係話正如我哋而家條文所講咧，就係應該只係指定畀執法人員需要嘅時候咧，先可以睇啊呢一點咧誒經過諮詢之後咧，我哋其實立場都好清晰㗎啦。
我哋覺得條文所講嘅，即係話只可以畀執法人員喺需要嘅時候要做打擊洗錢工作嘅時候去去查查核嘅話咧，呢個係個重要嘅原則嚟嘅。當然有啲人提出就話，究竟誒實益擁有人嗰個嗰個個定嘅水位係幾多啊？誒，大家都見到今次咧，我哋係根據。
啊！同時，我都理解到咧，有一部分係屬於呢個誒信託或者誒公司服務提供者嘅嘅人士提出，就話：既然有咗個新嘅發牌制度，係咪除咗要處理打擊洗錢要求以外咧，喺制定適當人適當人選呢個規則嘅時候，係咪可以定多啲專業嘅手則？
Thank you.
It seems like what the government is trying to do is you trying to fit.
到所有 views of the different professions who are here today. We've got accountants, we've got lawyers, we've got trustees, we've got notaries.
最簡單的辦法係，我哋可以透過法律專業人士的協調，或者透過法律專業人士嘅協
或doing more in order comply with the Fed investigation or monitoring. Thank you. Okay, 啊，主席。係，主席。誒，多謝各議員嘅問題。誒。
Schedule Two， you trying to fit one set of requirements for all the different professionals here when they have different duties， they have different skill set and they they have different needs and they do different things for their clients. Speaking for the legal profession。
做好多功夫啊！我哋都好感謝。咁但係我哋要答嘅問題就係噉樣足唔足夠咧？噉樣足唔足夠令到香港喺嚟緊嘅誒誒相互評估入邊，喺指定非金金融人士嗰方面，我哋可以過到關咧？噉樣誒，正如我啱啱所講咧。
誒，我哋覺得呢度係要分得好清楚嘅嚇。今次我哋提出個發牌制度咧，針對嘅咧係打擊洗錢嘅要求。咁所以，我哋喺制定適當人選呢個準則嘅時候咧，一定唔可以過高嘅，即係只要要只要適合適合得㗎啦。咁所以喺適合呢個角度睇咧，我哋覺得定得一個比較誒低啲嘅規定，令到業。
界可以可以可以遵從到嘅話咧，呢個比較合適嘅。我哋唔覺得呢一次嘅修訂咧，係攞嚟應該去處理佢哋專業發展嘅問題。呢個係另一層次嘅問題嚟㗎啦。誒，我都留意到誒，地產代理監管局啊誒嘅嘅朋友亦都好好幫忙啦。啊，亦都希望喺嚟緊制定指引嘅時候咧，可以針。
對啊，地產代理一啲比較特殊嘅情況，睇可唔可以喺符合我哋打擊洗錢條例下面嘅要求下面咧，可以做到一啲功夫啊？呢度我哋會同佢繼續傾。或者主席，或者我呢度停一停，我睇下有冇其他意見可以再我哋再回應。誒，剛才議會者咧，譬如似阿陳建明先生咧，都提出。
Look, the lawyers have been doing this for years, decades, and we've always been the pioneer in enforcing anti-money laundering rules. And as you know, the Law Society has very stringent requirements in the form of Practice Direction P, and that we have been using that for for many years, and it works well. And in the
二零一二報告 of the FAF in paragraph one hundred and forty nine one hundred and fifty, they specifically specifically pointed out that the the legal profession goes by practice direction P and has been doing a good job in enforcing these AML rules. So putting further requirements on the lawyers and all the other professions.
我們一定要非常小心。第一，我們不能傷害我們作為專業服務中心在世界頂尖的地位。所以，我們必須確保所有專業人士能夠繼續從事他們的工作，而無需大幅增加審查成本和時間。
所以，the point I want to make is first of all, can you tell me precisely what are the requirements that are currently lacking in the Law Society Practice Practice Direction P that you need to impose Schedule Two on the lawyers? Because Schedule Two actually deals with a lot of things that have
Nothing to do with the legal profession. For example, it talks about banks, talks about wire transfer, etc., etc. So, if you can tell us precisely, deputy secretary, precisely what there is in Schedule Two that you want to be included now in Practice Direction P, because the simple
審查措施。
下面咧係列出嘅。
啊，主席，啊，我呢度停一停。
此外咧，PDP亦都冇界定十億擁有人嘅門嘅個門個個門檻係幾多啊？
佢主要講好多係原則同埋概念，但係如果大家睇一睇我哋嘅附表二，即係法例嘅附表二咧，就講得好具體嘅呢個第一點。
組織同埋附表二嘅要求咧，就係對所有嘅客户，即係包括自然人同埋法人咧，都要識別同埋要核實佢哋嘅實益擁有人嘅身份啫。
講強制性，但係有啲文字咧又講建議性，咁所以喺呢度嚟講咧，對於財務行動特別組咧，就會係一個幾大嘅挑戰嘅。誒，此外咧，誒。
好嘅，秘書長，你可唔可以整理一下誒誒各議員嘅要求？會會，我哋下一次會提供誒，整個表，好好嚇，能夠表列出你。
We can then understand what you need from us, so that we can try to work with you on on this. It will be very helpful going forward. And if you can just give us this document and and then I can work with my colleagues. That would be very helpful. Thank you.
另外咧，我哋見到咧PDP咧，亦都冇要求律師行需要將客户盡職審查同埋備存記錄嘅規定咧，應用喺香港以外嘅分行同埋附屬企業。而呢個要求咧喺呢個特別組織下面咧，係必須要誒要要要跟循嘅。咁所以我啱啱所講咧，就係我哋列舉咗一啲唔同嘅地方。
And we'll give you an undertaking to update the practice direction P so that it fits into all the requirements that you say is lacking in the current model. So it'll be very helpful if you can tell us precisely what we're not doing, that you hope us to do, and that we.
We could then go about and look to how we update Practice Direction P. Because for the lawyers, I must emphasise that we've been doing this for years. We're very good at it. We're very diligent in terms of enforcing AML rules. So we need you to tell us in very clear terms what we should be.
打擊洗錢下面嘅附表二咧，係我哋而家要求誒金融機構做呢個客户進職審查同埋備存記錄方面咧，係一啲具體而又詳細嘅要求嘅。誒，我哋的確亦都明白誒法律界咧，其實做咗好多功夫啊！佢哋通過自己嘅下面咧，佢。
所謂做嘅啊practice direction p，即係個或者叫做佢個專業一個指引啦，係處理咗一部分啊，盡可能喺佢哋嘅權限下面咧，處理咗一啲誒誒關於客户進職審查同埋備存記錄嘅要求。誒，正如我喺啱啱嘅回答嗰度所講咧，誒，即使律師行業已經做。
啊！喺呢個財務行動特別組下面咧，佢寫得好清楚嘅。佢一定係一個明文立法規嘅。咁所以呢度我哋覺得第一點咧，就我哋好難避免一定要處理呢個法規嘅問題。第二當然都參考咗其他嘅地區，包括新加坡，你可以話慘痛嘅經驗啦嚇。咁所以如果我哋要做得到嘅話咧，我哋係要做功夫啊。
當然，我哋都睇過，就係究竟而家律師行業所講嘅佢哋嘅守則，同我哋睇緊誒打擊洗錢條例下面嘅嘅附表二，究竟個具體分別喺邊度咧？或者我可以簡單講一講嚇誒。譬如第一誒，如果你睇睇嘅法律界嘅P.D.P.佢哋講嘅咧誒，我哋睇落去就覺得。
第二咧，誒律師界P.D.P嘅嗰個嗰個要求咧，佢主要係針對係律師行同埋企業嘅層面嘅，而附表二嘅要求咧，同時適用於律師個人呢度係有個分別嘅。誒此外咧，P.T.P亦都容許律師咧，藉中介人去執行法定嘅客户進職。
誒，如果再睇一睇個PDP下面佢哋行文咧，你會見到佢會提到律師行進行客户進職審查同埋備存記錄方面咧，係屬於佢有講話係強制性嘅要求。咁但係有好多具體嘅要求咧，佢又擺喺附件嗰度，而附件度有講呢啲要求其實係建議性嘅嚇。咁所以如果大家會見到有陣時佢係話講。
喺特別行動措施誒喺呢個特別組織嘅要求同埋附件二規定有別咧，就PDB有關客户盡職審查具體要求，譬如話誒非直接會面嘅客户啊、政治人物嘅客户或者係要識別匿名客户等等咧，只係屬於建議性嘅程序同埋措施，並冇喺PDB嘅強制性要求。
lawyers。
發展， now。
它似乎係，啲老社會。
we should we should not have this legislation.
你 know， really have some concern and.
Why, why is that such a kind of change? Because I was lad.
Cost concern， as outlined just then by the honourable Dennis Quirk。
O.K.唔該，主席，請會計師公會可唔可以？會計師公會可唔可以誒對啊梁議員嘅？
under schedule two, could you please let us know, you know, what's your view on that? Is my comments fairly made?
They will still be self-regulated, subject to some you know alignment of or or just filling in the gaps by this legislation. But it does seems to me that now with the you know piece of legislation now draft law written in black and white.
此外咧，誒如果律師未能夠執行客户盡職審查嘅措施咧，PDP亦都冇要求佢哋咧必須終止業務關係啊。而PDP咧只係要求律師行喺客户係法人嘅情況下面咧，係要識別同埋核實佢係有冇誒嘅實益擁人擁擁有人嘅身份，而特別。
係，Chairman。Chairman，can I just make one講多一樣嘢得唔得？OK，你時間好長。Thank you，Deputy Secretary。We we want to work with you as well as a responsible profession. So it will be very helpful if you can give us a table setting out what the difference between Schedule Two and Practice Direction P. So
即係各個議員嘅問題嘅答案，好嗎？好嘅，好嘅，主席。下位啊，梁繼昌議。Thank you, Chairman. I'm a bit perplexed by by by the different view taken by the Law Society and the Hong Kong Institute of Certified Public Accountants. It does seem to me that the HKCPA welcomes
the anti-money laundering and counter-terrorist financing ordinance. Of course, you've got some, you know, minor comments. And the HKICPA, I think the some of the small and medium-sized practitioners, I do think they would be facing the same kind of
However, I don't seem to hear any big objection from from from your response as a whole, because I think the code of ethics prescribed by the institute seem to be quite comprehensive, and have already catered for the many situations or requirements and.
Can I follow your question? I I mentioned earlier we consult we have consulted our members and the consultation period have finished and we have not yet received any strong objection to the introduction of this. There there are comments on some some technical issues but so far we have not heard any strong views that.
Thank you. 好，主席，我問問政府。好，可以。嗯，I think in the briefing sessions given to us members by by the government, members were you know told by the government that I mean basically for the self-regulated professionals, including accountants and
by the government to believe that this is just a reiteration of the anti-money laundering procedures already adopted by the respective, you know, professional institutes. Well, at least I remember I received such a briefing last year. What? Why is there such a, you know?
下一位啊，何君瑤議。
誒多謝主席，我都係跟進翻咧，係講下律師會嗰個誒個文件咧，喺十月二十號。
年嘅嗰個practice direction P嘅嗰個區別，佢有隱約講出嚟話，稍後會附上呢一個噉嘅對比畀我睇。
顯示出係誒誒誒，即係背道而馳。噉你而家噉嘅加收緊嘅法例係咪有多少唔係好恰當咧？
有咗個明文法規嘅安排，但係個具體操作咧，仍然係由翻各事嘅專業組織去操作翻嘅。噉我哋覺得噉樣嘅安排咧，就應該係誒，我哋覺得已經係取得最大嘅平衡㗎啦。
係有啲係誒出入，就係話有啲自願性去處理，有啲係將來就會強制性啦。咁既然自願性都做得咁好嘅時候，強制性點解要要噉樣強喺律師行業裏邊嚟做呢個工作？即係呢一個。
嘅意思啦，如果有任何關於客户進職審查或者備存記錄同打擊洗錢有關嘅問題嘅話咧，係由翻相關嘅專業組織去根據佢哋各自嘅專業條例下面咧去處理嘅。
係啱啱司長。誒主席誒，多謝梁議員嘅嘅問題。誒喺我哋今次提出嘅修訂下面咧，針對律師、會計師同埋地產代理，我哋係秉持於專業自主嘅嘅原則嘅。所謂專業自主嘅原則。
即係包括譬如話，如果係會計師嘅話咧，就應該係會計師公會會處理翻嘅。嚇，只不過你都要講，你要做客户盡職審查，你要講誒備存記錄，咁嗰啲具體係點樣參考咧？具體你要睇翻《打擊洗錢條例》下邊附表二佢有講你要做乜嘢。
嘅噉，但係我哋都賦權咗各自嘅專業組織，佢可以定出指引啊喺具體運作方面咧，可以講清楚點樣去做，令到啊從業員咧同埋專業人士咧有所適從嘅。咁所以，因為既然阿阿阿梁院咁提咧，我我都要再三強調嘅就係我哋喺做嗰時候正正。
就係建基於一個專業自主嘅原則嚇，所以我哋將真係具體去做呢個問題咧，就交翻畀嗰啲相關嘅專業組織去做翻嘅。咁但係當然，如果要符合啊財務行動特別組織嘅要求咧，我哋都要有個明文嘅法規嘅。咁再今次嘅修訂咧，就係。
誒特別係第二十一段裏邊咧，要求兩樣嘢就係誒誒政府部門咧提供嘅。咁郭榮亨議員剛才已經誒誒問問咗一啲問題咧，就孫生亦都提列出咗咧附件二同埋我哋誒律師會已經誒奉行好耐，超過十。
噉啊，但係始終有一樣嘢，我都係覺得誒誒，第一點就呢個問題喺從統計嘅數字方面嚟睇咧，實際上我哋已經有個practice direction p出現咗，誒係運作良好，亦都係統計數字裏邊冇話顯著嘅呢一個practice direction。
好啦。
陳振儀。
就冇啱啱。
誒多謝主席，誒多謝何議員嘅嘅嘅問題，嗯。
我哋向律師會提供畀佢哋有個更加詳細嘅回答，睇下先生可唔可以喺呢一方面諗諗？B長。
仲可能低嘅，嚇咁所以翻翻去講誒律師行業嗰個問題，誒正如我先前誒都都所講咧，就係。
當然，我哋會繼續同律師會溝通。啊，我哋都希望誒喺喺實質運作嘅時候咧，儘量減低誒專業專業人士同埋行業喺喺符合要求方面所需要付出嘅額外嘅功夫。Okay.
P係誒唔應用或者冇佢跟進，而導致到風險好高。喺噉嘅情況下，點解我哋唔能夠繼續尊重專業啊？佢哋自行去去去去運作咧？噉你提到誒講話嗰個附件二嗰度有啲同誒現在嘅practice direction P裏邊嘅。
我又覺得唔係好有誒一個説服力喺呢一度，除非你話唔係啊？誒向來就係自願性，但係我哋睇到個實際上嘅證據顯示出咧，係有好多人違規而導致到有一個最大嘅漏洞，所以我而家要加重分量啦。咁人哋做得咁好，自願性嘅環境裏邊做得咁咁理想，你又冇任何嘅證據。
第二咧就係律師會裏邊要求嗰個B二十一B個文件裏邊喺其他海外嘅經驗咧，人哋嗰啲引入咗C.D.D之後咧，嗰個嗰個效果點樣啊？佢嗰個國際嘅嗰個誒品評啊，嗰個誒嗰個評論又點樣？呢個我諗呢個資料咧應該。
喺制定呢兩條修訂條例嘅時候咧，誒政府當然我哋充分明白到，我哋要做呢啲條文嘅時候咧，你一定要取得一個平衡嘅第一個平衡咧，就你要就要令到我哋喺嚟緊誒遵循國際嘅嘅標準嘅時候咧，可以達到誒財務行動特別組織嘅要。
要求針對指定非金融業人士嘅要求，呢個第一點係我哋要做到。另一方面咧，我哋都充分明白誒每一個要求咧，對於個行業嚟講咧，都係會有成本嘅嚇。所以我哋係希望儘量做到咧，將誒受影響行業嘅合規成本咧，係降到儘量。
當我哋去睇財務行動特別組織關於指定非金融業人士嘅要求嘅時候，佢點做咧？其中一點嘅重點咧，就係我哋理解到咧，你如果唔將佢納入明文嘅法規嘅話咧，我哋去做評估嘅時候咧，我哋會好難去攞到一個好嘅嘅結果嘅。
即係好難過到關噉。我噉樣講係建基於我哋已經睇到，譬如鄰近嘅地區，誒新加坡，佢已經面對一個咁大嘅挑戰啦。嚇，因為佢誒某啲指定嘅非金融人士，佢哋係係有指引嘅，但係嗰啲唔係立法規嘅，嗰啲指引都做得好詳細嘅。咁但係佢得到結果咧係唔掂嘅。
嚇！咁所以呢個係清晰嘅，而我哋針對律師行業咧，又睇一睇同我哋嘅法制係類近嘅地方，譬如新加坡、啊，譬如英國、啊或者馬來西亞，人哋點樣做咧？誒，我哋見到呢三個地區咧，佢哋都已經好清晰，將律師要做呢個誒誒客户盡職審查同埋誒備存記錄嘅要求咧。
那。
因，呃。
下一位啊，陶景新議。
誒，我哋覺得喺呢一次嘅修訂咧，就似乎唔係太適合去處理呢個專業發展方面嘅問題。
報嘅時候咧，我就誒有個歷史感。噉我哋都知道咧，即係譬如話佢而家呢度咧，應該係誒多啲乜嘢啊噉。
根據今次嘅條例修案咧，誒修定咧，會有一個發牌制度，係係針對嗰啲信託或者公司服務提供者。
而家嘅誒需要啦，但係我哋環顧我哋同譬如一啲誒主要競爭對手，譬如新加坡嗰個比較，我諗大家可以睇翻咧，就係誒。
噉我我我咧就因為我有好多嘅嗰啲誒意見書我都睇咗咧，咁或者我將用用或者我簡單講一講，或者問一問政府同埋相關有啲團體嘅意見噉樣。
testing testing，啊，主席，啊，首先咧就誒我好多謝誒咁多位誒嚟畀意見嘅誒朋友啦，包括專業團體咧。就我首先係講唔好意思，因為咧我隔離咧就同一時間開嗰個司法事務委員會咧，就律政司司長咧就嚟，有啲嘢誒要重要嘅簡報噉樣。
係寫在法規嗰度嘅，即係要喺法規度表達得清清楚楚，呢個係一個法法定嘅安排嘅。咁所以呢度咧，誒我哋明白，誒誒律師會都誒寫咗好多資料畀我哋嚇，即係律師會我我哋感激佢哋提出好多睇法嘅。嗱，我哋都好尊重，亦都誒非常之感謝律師會喺過去咁多年咧喺做。
誒誒，客户進職審查方面同埋備存記錄做咗好多好多功夫嘅，咁但係即使係噉，誒我哋都再仔細睇一睇我哋要對要面對嘅問題，誒為咗要應對到誒特別組織嘅要求咧，我哋覺得而家我哋提出嘅方案咧係一個必須嘅做法嚟嘅。
唔該，主席誒，我都係問翻我上次誒問嘅問題啦。咁其實上次我都問過政府當局關於信託及公司服務持牌人，即係T C S P嗰個誒可以做盡職審查嘅資格問題，因為誒上次政府嗰個答案咧就係話為咗即係又要。
呢個法例可以及時推出啦，令到業界人士而家做緊嘅業界人士咧，係可以繼續佢嘅工作。但係我上次都誒問過，但係未有一個好實質嘅答覆嘅，就係誒喺第一階段我理解嘅，因為誒啱啱個法例推行啦，咁亦都要誒照顧業界嘅，即係。
秘書公會咧，畀嗰封啊信咧，佢亦都誒列表列出咗同我哋同新加坡嗰個差別咁喺度㗎啦。噉我想問啊，就係話喺第一個階段或者初階段，你誒政府用呢一個噉嘅準則容許佢做防洗黑錢嘅一個審查嘅。
嘅誒專業人士啦，雖然佢冇專業資格，咁仲係可以叫做誒勉強可以接受。但係係有幾耐時間，你會檢討，譬如佢哋檢查出嚟嘅誒效果，同埋咧佢哋出嚟嘅誒誒情況咧，係咪滿意？然後再檢討下呢個噉嘅。
資格咧，需唔需要進一步再去重檢，或者係甚至引入一個正式嘅發牌制度咧？唔該，主席。好，嗯，議長。誒，主席誒，多謝陳議員嘅問題。誒，呢個意見喺今次有啲誒誒，與會人士都提咗嘅，即係大家覺得，既然政府以
但係，我正如我喺之前都有個個回覆嘅，就係我哋覺得做呢個發牌制度一定要考慮清楚。我哋提出呢個發牌制度嘅目的係乜嘢啊？我哋今次做呢個發牌制度嘅目的係要係要確保我哋嘅誒信託或者公司服務提供者咧，佢可以符合到誒。
特別組織針對佢哋嘅要求，咁即係話喺打擊洗錢方面嘅嘅要求。咁所以我哋覺得我哋要做嘅咧就係只係針對究竟我要做到個程度最低，做呢個適當人選嘅嘅嗰個測試是最低係幾多，令到可以符合到呢個要求。咁所以我哋喺條例下面咧，只係列出最低嘅要求嘅。
咁咧。
譬如而家噉樣。
咁於是佢咪幫佢即係做啲文件嚟轉個董事啦噉。
咁好啦，噉就算係都好。
咁但係咧，如果你話喂，我一定要做翻CDD咧。
政府會唔會就係採納一個所謂risk-based approach？
律師會嘅層次就話：，喂，噉我點？你你點樣有幾大嘅即係調查價值啊？嗰啲嘢咧噉樣。
就做咗嗰個誒指引咧，就用一個叫risk-based approach approach，OK。
咁即係換句話講咧，佢喺裏邊佢個例子係咩咧？即係前面第十段前面嗰個例子就話嗱，例如你叫個律師。
可能佢咧就幫手管理緊一間誒公司嘅噉啊，幫佢。噉佢話：喂，你轉咗個董事啦，噉樣。
好啦，嗱，就係呢個用一個咁簡單嘅例子，係人都明啦。O K，噉我想問下政府或者律師會，如果嗰啲朋友咧可以補充都得嘅。
就誒，或者我同政府研究一下嗱。譬如佢舉一個例，佢佢其實言下之意咧，好簡單，佢就話咧，英國嘅律師會咧。
咁死啦！就算我真係做完之後有懷疑都好，我又冇得報嘅喎。因為點解咧？嗰度冇錢嘛，唔關唔關係錢嘅問題，而係轉個人啫嘛。O.K.
噉我舉一個例，我舉一個例啫，等容易啲瞭解一下誒嗰個大嘅環境啊。嗱，譬如律師會主席，我係律師會會員啦，宣佈利益啊。咁律師會嗰個誒陳詞嗰度第十段咧。
冇咩反反對㗎啦，個行業都O K嘅，即係係好支持添嘅噉樣。O K啊，噉我即係整體得到噉嘅印象。咁當然啦，今次咧，我睇詳細嚟講咧，其實我都有好多我自己誒，即係嘅意見啦噉。
誒，但係阿陳議員同埋有有幾位與會人士所提出嘅咧，就唔係講緊最低要求嘅，你係講緊呢個專業發展嘅專業嘅要求嚇。我哋就覺得應該兩件事係分開處理啊，唔係話唔處理，而係話我哋喺呢條例下面要處理嘅咧，係打擊洗錢嘅問題。如果你係講緊專業發展咧，呢個係另一個議題嚟嘅。
就誒，我初頭咧就誒，因為政府咧就誒嚟呢條例嘅時候咧，噉佢都好緊張咧，因為誒或者佢好多嘅議員嗰度咧都有啲即係簡簡報噉樣啦。噉就誒，因為我都誒做呢啲法例咧，做咗廿幾三十年啦，咁所以咧佢都嚟簡。
咁於是咧就我得到個印象咧，即係政府話畀我哋聽咧，即係我相信從仔同啊梁繼昌言都一樣咧，就話冇問題啊。佢哋都同意㗎啦，噉樣啊，即係全部都同意㗎啦。因為咧，今次只不過咧就係誒落實翻一啲咧，即係做開嘢啫啊。咁所以咧就誒影響唔大嘅。O.K.啊，就冇咩。
啊。
即係風險為本。
個理解上嘅政府啊！
要做C.D.D.嘅咧。
OK，阿比著。
誒多謝主席啊！多謝誒誒陶議員。
咁其實啊，嗰個係咪都同樣？
又或者，譬如如果呢個呢個第十個啊啊段層次裏邊嘅例子，其實咧，如果根據翻嗰個risk base approach。
提出嗰個修訂嘅嘅嘅方向同埋具體嘅安排咧，誒，我哋的確係盡量平衡咗誒業界嘅顧慮同埋我哋必必須面對嘅挑戰。
就仲令我更加糊塗啊！即係我本來問你個問題，點解咧？嗱，法規第一重啦，第二重就係嗰啲指引啦。OK，第三重就係咩咧？嗰啲指引或者法規之後有冇成效啦？嗱，好啦。
行動特別組織嘅要求嘅時候咧，我哋再睇埋其他地區嘅親身嘅經歷，就係我哋覺得我哋係要做出一個明文嘅法規，先至可以有機會可以攞到一個比較好啲嘅嘅嘅嘅評估嘅結果出嚟。
或者我都要重新再講一次誒。我哋所講嘅咧就係我我哋明白律師會誒提咗好多觀點誒，但係我哋面對嘅眼前嘅嘅現實咧就係你要香港要喺嚟緊嘅相互評估入邊可以達到誒。
但係，我我明白好多細節方面咧，喺具體做嘅時候咧，我一定會同律師會合作嚇，確保喺喺係可以大家都做得做得妥當嚇。咁所以誒，我哋譬如以英國為例，就算英國本身佢都已經通過咗法例，講到明律師行業係要做呢個。
個客户進職審查同埋備存記錄係用法法規規定嘅，即係我覺得喺喺嚟緊，尤其是誒特別行政行動組織，佢喺個相互評估嘅方法方面咧，佢而家係講緊既要睇你係咪技術上合規，仲要睇你嘅成效如何。嚇，呢個係一個即係新嘅做法嚟嘅。
咁所以我哋而家第一步，我哋修定法例，第一步咧就希望可以做到喺技術上係做到合規，但係另一方面，除咗做咗技術上合規之外咧，我哋更加要要證明，要講畀人聽我個成效如何嘅，嚇，所以我就覺得我哋嚟緊其實都挑戰重重嘅，噉我哋都希望誒誒大家都明白政府。
主席啊！主席，我唔好意思，我真係覺得政府咧冇答到嘅原因咧。你講個大方向，即係話誒，我哋誒要過到關啦嚇，即係所謂啦。我哋就要整啲誒法規嘅嘢，因為人哋有法規，我冇法規，咁人哋就話一一句督住你冇法規喎，噉樣好啦。而家個問題咧就係你頭先啱嗰個答案。
啊，被告。
哇！辣到好交關嘅～
咁咧就噉，即係話咧。
噉你就話，我哋主要睇成效噉。
律師會咧就話啦：，喂，而家冇法規有指引，個成效好好喎。
而家我哋咧，根據律師會個成個嘅層次咧，似乎就係你冇法規。
噉我就問啦，如果我哋今次審議就係我畀個法規你，但個法規跟住之後原來。
噉啊，有個指引，OK，個指引行幾年添，因為呢個同其他行業有啲唔同，因為佢做咗做得幾比較好啲，政府咁講啊，同我話，OK，唔係我贊你哋啊。
嗱呢個就係佢哋講，噉啊照計都吻合嘅，因為你同我都咁講嘅，啊話呢個行業咧比較好啲啦，咁噉啊其他行業反而咧就擔心啲噉，好啦，咁而家個問題就你話要整個法規。
行嘅喎，即係個個反應啊。OK，佢哋嘅擔心咧，同你所講話，誒，佢哋唔擔心嘅噉樣，都唔係好好擔心。不過律師會已經有個有軌道嘅指引，都擔心，甚至覺得有啲嘢係過分咗嘅噉。
噉我就問你，我話喂，噉係咪整咗法規之後，原本嗰個指引，咁而家律師會就話喂，譬如佢佢一個例子啊，等佢容易明白啦嚇，就話喂，咁呢個如果係噉就即係煩，吹毛求疵喎噉。
辣到咧，真係根根本咧，就就大家都唔知點做嘅。O K，噉啊，最後咧就成個所有唔係淨係律師會，即係所有嘅律師會做咗咁耐，有個模範唔好模範啦，所以唔係即係個有個法規已經係唔係法規指引係係已經係大致上O K，同埋你哋都話都幾全面嘅。
咁如果都煩嘅煩，佢哋自己都好煩啊，覺得呢個夠唔夠咧？啊，或者多咗好多，你都繼續煩佢咧。噉我如果我個個行業都係用法法規，跟住個指引，仲比律師會仲辣。咁然後跟住咧，仲仲要再第三號咧，就話個成效點樣？噉我哋咪好大件事，咪個個行業都唔知點做。
不犯犯到七彩直情做唔到生意，做唔到任何專業都做唔到嘢。嗱，當然到最尾你話你做唔到一件事啦。我哋救香港㗎嘛，救地球咪救救香港啊？係嘛？唔做呢啲就救唔到香港㗎啦。啊，你冇冇生意都做唔到㗎啦，制裁㗎啦噉係嘛？噉我而家就係希望政府咧，就我舉一個例子，等你容易明。
白咧，你你你可唔可以即係話嗱？你放心，呢啲嘢咧，我哋都係真係risk base嘅。嗱，如果根據risk base，既然英國律師會都得咯，咁即係驗身，我哋第時就唔會畀人夾我哋啦。噉啊，噉你整我哋放心啲得唔得咧？如果唔係咧，變咗咧，你你同我講嗰套，同而家噉我聽到業界嗰啲完全唔。
誒多謝主席誒，多謝陶議員。誒，我哋關於誒，大家睇到喺條例下面，其實關於客户盡職審查同埋備備存記錄，就係根據條例附件二所講嘅嘢嘅附件二，其實喺誒金融機構已經做緊嘅啦。啊，大家已經有一個誒實際運作嘅經驗嘅嚇。我哋當然啱啱之前我。
唔係啊，好嘛。
我哋今。
誒由法規。
好啦，誒時間咧亦都差唔多，咁咧就誒。
當條例通過咗之後，律師行業要做嘅功夫咧，其實唔會比而家多好多。
今日咧就暫時係收到十七個團體或者公眾人士誒對於條例草案交嘅書面意見。
誒意識到嗰個附表裏邊咧所要求嘅標準咧，就係同我舉例，因為而家律師會已經有咁耐有個指引啦。你話仲有啲唔係好？
別組織嘅要求嚇，但係我哋明白到其實而家律師行業已經做緊功夫嘅，佢已經針對呢個打擊洗錢方面咧，累積咗相當多嘅經驗嘅。咁所以我哋相信。
我指出咗誒，律師會所發嘅佢哋叫PracticeDirectionsP同埋呢個附件二咧，係的確有啲地方係唔係盡相同嘅。係我想講出嚟嘅咧，就係話一個喺無論你個個呢個律師會發嘅PDP咧，佢唔係一個明文嘅法規，呢個係一個形式嘅問題嚇。
除此之外咧，如果睇真啲P.D.P.入邊有某啲嘅要求咧，相對於附表二咧係有出入嘅嚇。咁所以我哋想提出嘅咧就係話，如果做咗啲條例之後咧，當然喺法喺做正式指引嘅時候咧，大家一定要律師方面咧係會參考翻附件二嘅要求誒，然後做到咧係符合到特。
咁所以，我我我想，我明白陶議員所講，就話：喂，你嘅指引，你都要確保大家做得到啊！咁呢個其實都係我哋嘅嘅一向嘅嘅嘅秉持嘅立場嘅。嚇，但係除咗做得到之外咧，我哋其實亦都要確保我哋過到特別組織嘅要求，就係一喺嗰個規定方面咧，我哋明白，如果你冇呢個明文法規咧。
我哋係好難過到嘅。噉你當我，如果你過唔到會點啊？噉樣佢要跟進嘅嘛。咁所以，我當我今次我話我試一試薄薄得唔得？如果唔得，佢下年又翻嚟要我要再做嘅，再唔得下年又要你再做嘅。咁所以我哋就覺得，如果見到其他地區嘅人士，嘅其他地區都已經喺呢度咧，呢個好清晰嘅信息。
畀大家嘅就係你，如果冇明文法規嘅話咧，你好難喺個評估入邊咧攞到攞到一個合格嘅成績。咁所以呢度咧，呢個法規係個要求啦。但喺具體運作方面咧，我哋喺條例下面都講咗嘅，其實都係由各自嘅專業組織咧，佢係定翻佢自己嘅指引嘅。正正係呢個精神咧，我哋希望由翻各自嘅
專業組織去定翻個指引嘅話咧，希望喺做嘅時候咧，喺具體做嘅時候咧，係可以顧及行業嘅擔心，同埋令到行業可以容易啲做到呢個功夫。主席，我攞資料啫，一句係就誒，既然因為方便以後，我哋開會嚇，就係誒。既然頭先誒秘書長話誒嗰個。
你又講得好誒客氣嘅，你話咧唔係好誒一致，唔係唔係好唔係好一樣啦嚇。O K，咁咧究竟有啲乜嘢，或者我理解你即係不足啦？誒講得白啲，有啲咩不足或者唔唔符合嘅地方，可唔可以起碼用嗰個例子啊？因為嗰個已經比較詳細啦嚇，其他行業有啲未有添。
嗱，對，做一份文件，話聲畀我聽，等我知道。例如會唔會嗰有幾開黑係嘛？可以判斷一下嘛。議員咧，可能頭先你忙其他嘅會議，誒國慶議已經。啊，要求咗，OK，good，very good，very good。誒，各方已經達結咗㗎啦。得得得，OK，嚇，唔該。你嘅你嘅想法同啊國慶議長。
咁誒，冇其他事項咧，今日曬會。
提解一啲回應啦，好嘛？提解一啲書面回應啦。
咁誒會議咧，就進入下一個議程咧，係其他事項。
其實時候咧，就下一次會議日期係一七年嘅十一月十四號，禮拜二上晝十點四十五分。
咁秘書處咧已經喺會會議前咧，將呢啲意見書咧畀咗各位委員㗎啦。噉啊，我亦都希望各方誒睇咗呢啲意見書之後咧，稍後係誒。
噉我哋下一次咧就可以進入去逐字審議嘅工作啊。咁誒兩條兩個草案嗰啲係誒係公司。
條例嗰個重話行先咧，還是係誒洗一錢係點啊？唐議員，主席點會點會咁快突然間會逐條審議啊？主席，因為你就算譬如嗰個誒嗰個。
就先話誒嗰個行業指引，舉一個例同政府嗰個立法之後嘅要求啊，嗰啲都要細節要討論咗先嘅喎。唔係啊，你嘅個誒政府會提供資料。唔係啊，嗰啲係要討論啊，唔係提供資料啊。咁下一節下一節開會嘅時候可以討論啦。係咯係咯，噉係咪就係係兩個鐘頭？
討論曬嗰份嘢咧，唔緊要。不過我驚你即係你，你話第一秒鐘就入入入依個全誒唔係係你聽我講埋先，大家唔好唔急啦。唔係因為嗰度咧，我相信咧係要討論好耐。都會睇，但係唔係睇曬成節會啊嘛？主席未必㗎，即係你畀合理時間我哋咧，因為佢嗰度咧係個靈魂嚟嘅。噉係靈魂，靈魂。
如果靈魂出咗竅噉，我哋咪要下一下一個下一個工作要做啦。唔係出咗竅啊！如果個係主主要而家揾到嘅分別啦。係啦，歸位啦，唔係入唔係出竅。OK，噉啊誒呢個誒你下一次嘅會議咧就係十一月十四號上晝十點四十五分。嗯噉。